本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on the Bible...
在起初
In the beginning...
天主创造天地
God created the heavens and the earth.
亚当和厄娃违背天主的旨意
Adam and Eve disobeyed God
偷食禁果
and ate the forbidden fruit.
从那之后  因为加音杀了亚伯尔
Since then, since Cain killed Abel,
天主目睹了人类内心深处太多的恶念
God has seen too much evil in human hearts.
天主警告我
God warned me,
要我造一座方舟
he told me to build a boat.
亚巴郎
Abraham...
天主同我说话了
God has spoken to me.
他将指引我们去新的家园
He will lead us to a new home.
他保证我的后裔会多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
-你会有孩子的  -我不能
- You will have a child. - I can't.
我的年纪太大了
It's too late for me.
亚巴郎  土地不够
Abraham, there just isn't enough land.
我们人太多了
There are too many of us.
是时候分道扬镳了
It's time we go our separate ways.
发生了什么事
What happened?
他们人太多了
There were so many of them.
罗特呢
And Lot?
还活着  但被抓走了
Alive, but taken prisoner.
如果我连自己的家人都领导不了
How can I lead a people...
又如何去领导一个民族呢
when I can't even lead my own family?
相信天主
Trust in God!
亚巴郎
Abraham.
我们还是要去索多玛
We're carrying on to Sodom.
你要毁灭它吗
You're going to destroy it?
整座城市
The whole city?
毁灭恶人的同时
Will you destroy the good men...
也要牵连那些好人吗
...along with the evil ones?
亚巴郎  你的妻子撒辣在哪儿
Abraham, where is your wife?
尽管撒辣不能生育  但她会生下一个男孩
Though she is barren, Sarah will have a son.
你要给他起名叫做依撒格
You will name him Isaac.
天主想要一个祭品
God wants a sacrifice.
我表现出来的信德还不够吗
Have I not shown you enough faith?
亚巴郎
Abraham!
圣经
亚巴郎死后约400年
Nearly 400 years aftrer Abraham,
饥荒迫使以色列人远离盟约之地
famine has forced the Israelites far from the promised land
来到埃及
to Egypt.
在那里  他们成为了法郎的奴隶
Here they are enslaved by Pharaoh.
亚巴郎和天主成了遥远的记忆
Abraham and God have become a distant memory.
他的子民都沦为重负之下的役畜
All his people reduced to beasts of burden.
只有一人幸免于此
Except one.
梅瑟
Moses.
你不能再去争强斗勇了
You're not going to fight again.
我无法拒绝  母亲  他是法郎的儿子
I can't refuse. He's Pharaoh's son, mother.
他们之间的较量必须停止
The fighting between them has to stop.
梅瑟并不想去
Moses doesn't want to fight.
是你那屡战屡败的儿子逼他的
It's your son who forces him into it, and keeps losing.
也许你是我姐姐的心头宝
You may be my sister's favorite,
但我才是未来的法郎
but I will be Pharaoh.
我会是埃及的神
I will be God!
别打了
Please.
还手  我命令你
Fight me! I order you!
梅瑟
Moses!
够了
Enough!
他得明白自己的身份
He needs to learn his place!
是你先挑起来的
But you were the one that started it!
我是未来的法郎王
I will be Pharaoh!
那么你的行为处事最好有个法郎王的样子
Then you'd better start behaving like one.
都是你的错  你就不该让她抚养他
This is your fault. You should never have let her keep him.
闭嘴
Silence.
-你根本非我族人  -我叫你闭嘴
- You're not one of us! - Silence, I said!
他在说什么
What's he talking about?
你最好现在就告诉他
You'd better tell him now.
你
You!
跟我过来
Come with me!
母亲  告诉我什么
Mother. Tell me what?
什么
What?!
梅瑟
Moses.
我把你当儿子一样疼爱
I love you like a son.
但是你并非我亲生
But you're not my blood!
你是奴隶之子
You were born a slave.
把他们都抓起来
Fetch them all!
我父亲杀了很多孩子
Father killed so many children.
他担心会有叛乱
He feared a rebellion.
你的族人人口众多
Your people were too many.
我的
My...
族人
People?
我救了你
I saved you.
你的族人就在外面  梅瑟
Your people are out there, Moses.
我们的奴隶
Our slaves.
那些以色列人
The Israelites.
你有个哥哥  叫亚郎
You had a brother, Aaron.
还有一个姐姐
And a sister.
叫米利安
Miriam.
但他们跟我们不一样
But they are not like us.
快点  你  快点
Come on! You! Come on!
快点  快起来  婊子
Come on, up you get, whore!
他们崇拜亚巴郎的神
They worship the God of Abraham,
而他遗弃了他们
and he has deserted them.
以色列贱民
Israelite scum!
不要  求求你  我求你了
No, please! Please! I beg you!
跳
Jump!
快跑  快跑
Run, run!
我会把尸体藏起来
I will hide the body.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
主人  这是梅瑟的护身符
My Lord, the amulet of Moses.
要不要追捕他
Shall we hunt him down?
不  让他走
No, let him go.
他已经无法造成威胁了
He's no threat now.
新生活欢迎你  梅瑟
Welcome to your new life, Moses!
你现在什么都不是了
You are nothing now!
什么都不是
Nothing.
西乃山
四十年后
你的族人都在外面呢  梅瑟
Your people are out there, Moses.
你根本非我族人
You're not one of us!
他们崇拜亚巴郎的神
They worship the God of Abraham.
你就不该让她收养他
You should never have let her keep him.
而他遗弃了他们
And he has deserted them.
我是未来的法郎王
I will be Pharaoh!
梅瑟
Moses.
我在这里
I am here.
我是你父亲的天主 亚巴郎的天主  依撒格的天主
I am the God of Abraham, of Isaac,
雅各伯的天主
and Jacob.
你是真实存在的吗
You are real?
我是
I am.
我看见我的百姓在埃及所受的痛苦
I have seen the misery of my people.
我派你到法郎那里去
I am sending you to Pharaoh
带他们离开埃及
to bring them out of Egypt.
但是我要怎么做才能让他们自由
But how can I set them free?
我已经不是王子了
I am not a prince now.
我什么都不是
I'm nothing.
我会与你同在
I will be with you.
有了你的力量
With your power,
我会让我的百姓获得自由
I will set my people free.
在埃及  新王已经登基
In Egypt, there is a new man on the throne.
梅瑟的老对手如今已经成了法郎王
Moses's old rival is now Pharaoh.
谢谢你  父亲
Thank you, father.
终有一天  你会拥有一支军队
One day you'll have an army of them.
真正的军队
Real ones.
快干活
Come on!
一切如昨  依旧水深火热
Nothing has changed. So much suffering.
嘿 你
Hey, you!
你
回去干活
Back to work!
等等  请等等
Wait. Wait. Please.
我来跟他说  大人
I will take care of him,  Master.
你在干什么  想让我们都挨打吗
What are you doing? Trying to get us all a beating?
你是谁  你在这干什么
Who are you? What are you doing here?
我是梅瑟
My name is Moses.
梅瑟
Moses?
你就是梅瑟
You are Moses?
我要见你们的长老
I need to see your elders.
跟我来
Come with me.
这人说他是梅瑟
This man says he's Moses!
那个逃跑的王子
The Runaway Prince.
你因谋杀罪被通缉
You're wanted for murder.
如果你真是他  为什么回来
If you're who you say you are, why would you return?
天主派我回来的
God has sent me.
我到这儿来
I am here
为给你们自由
to set you free.
天主派你来的
God has sent you?
没错  天主派我来  向你们传话
Yes, God sent me. To speak to you.
你们还记得天主吗
Have you forgotten God?
即使你们忘记了他
Even if you have...
他却未曾忘记你们
He has not forgotten you.
恐怕你忘记了
In case you had forgotten,
法郎才是我们唯一让我们害怕的神
Pharaoh is the only God we have to fear.
你认为他会轻易放我们走吗
And you think he's just going to let us go?
是谁创造了大地
Who created the earth,
海洋
sea,
天空
sky?
是谁创造了你们
Who created you?
是法郎王
Pharaoh?
还是天主
Or God?
你疯了
You're demented.
不
No!
他没有
He isn't!
他是我的弟弟
He's my brother.
亚郎
Aaron.
梅瑟
Moses!
天主向我托梦说你会回来
God sent me a dream to say you would return.
这是米利安  你的姐姐
This is Miriam, your sister.
弟弟
Brother.
这是我的孩子
My children.
我的家人
My family.
我的族人
My people.
我们的族人
Our people.
-天主的子民  -天主的子民
- God's people! - God's people!
老法郎王或许喜欢你
Old Pharaoh may have been fond of you.
但你现在要对付的是他的儿子
But it's his son you'll have to deal with now.
法郎为什么要见你
Why would Pharaoh even see you?
他会想见我的
He'll want to see me.
你有儿子
You have a son.
有继承人了
An heir.
我们的王朝会万代长存
Our dynasty will last forever.
你到这儿来做什么  梅瑟
Why are you here, Moses?
来请求宽恕吗
Have you come to ask for forgiveness?
不
No.
天主出于某种目的救了我
God saved me for a purpose.
是吗
Yes?
我是来要求你
I come to demand
还他的子民自由
that you release his people from slavery.
要求
Demand?
还我族人自由
Let my people go.
你一直是名斗士  梅瑟
You always were a fighter, Moses.
但你战败时从不自知
But you never knew when you were beaten.
倘若藐视天主  你会受到惩罚
If you defy God, you will be punished.
这么多年后  你回来就为了威胁我吗
You return, after all these years, to threaten me?
告诉我
Tell me.
你那看不见的天主会来惩罚我么？
Is it your invisible God that's going to punish me?
那个抛弃他子民
The one who abandons his people?
逃避责任  逃避过去
The one who runs from his responsibilities, from his past?
逃避家庭的家伙
From his family?
告诉他们谁才是天主
Teach them who God is.
我就是天主
I am God!
梅瑟  你惹怒了法郎
Moses! You've made Pharaoh angry.
他会惩罚我们的  悬崖勒马吧
He will punish us. Don't make it worse.
天主和我说过
God has spoken to me.
倘若别无他法  他会迫使法郎
He will force Pharaoh to free us...
还我们自由的
If he has to.
我们该怎么办
What should we do?
姐姐  哥哥
Sister. Brother.
你们所有人
All of you.
信赖天主
Trust in God!
法郎就在那儿
Pharaoh is over there.
你在殿上面见他的时候  他都充耳不闻
If he didn't listen to you when you were six feet away,
现在又怎么会听你的呢
why would he hear you now?
你将会看到
You will see.
把你的杖...
Put your staff...
放进河里
to the water.
主人
Master!
快上来  血  有血
Come out of the water! There's blood! There's blood!
有血  血流成河了
There's blood! Blood everywhere!
-陛下  -快游上岸
- Your majesty! - Swim to us!
主人
Master!
你不是天主
You are not a God.
只是凡人
You are just a man.
你一定会释放我的族人
And you will set my people free.
走开
Move away!
梅瑟
Moses!
你相信了吗  若苏厄
Do you doubt, Joshua?
我这一生都被法郎奴役
All my life, I have been Pharaoh's.
我再也不会作奴隶了
I will never be a slave again.
天主与我们同在
God is with us.
这只是个开始
This is just the beginning.
天主安排了十次灾难
Our Lord is sending ten plagues
为改变法郎的想法
to change Pharaoh's mind.
释放我的族人
Let my people go.
不
No!
蝗虫
Locusts.
快离开那  主人
Come away! Master!
走开  走开
Go away! Go away!
不
No!
梅瑟
Moses?
法郎怎么说  他应该醒悟过来了吧
What is Pharaoh's answer? Surely he will see sense now?
不
No.
他还是不愿意
He refuses.
还是这样
Again?
放弃吧  梅瑟  不然一切都来不及了
Give up, Moses, before it's too late.
灾难不会停止的
God will keep on doing this
除非法郎王就范
until Pharaoh breaks.
怎么了
What's wrong?
不久  最后一场瘟疫就会发生
Soon there will be a final plague.
死亡天使会降临
The angel of death is coming.
所有长子都会死
Every firstborn son will die.
不要啊
No. Please.
不会发生在我们身上吧  为什么要惩罚我们
But not us? Why would he punish us?
死亡是冲着所有人来的
Death is coming for us all.
为什么是我们
Why us?
同胞们
Friends!
只有我们谨遵天主的指示
We can be spared God's vengeance,
才能逃过这一劫
but only if we do exactly as he tells us.
别洒了
Don't spill!
每家每户都要用血做记号
Every single house must be marked with blood.
以色列人拿羊血在门上做记号
The Israelites paint lamb's blood on their doorways,
以表明自己是天主的子民
identifying them as God's people.
我们确信天主将使我们的族人获得自由
We promised God would free our people,
但天主却送来了死亡
but now he sends us death.
我们必须信赖他
We must trust in him.
来了
It's coming.
-我们会有事吗  -别怕  孩子
- Will we be safe? - Don't be afraid, my son.
愿天主怜悯
God have mercy.
法郎一意孤行
Pharaoh has not listened.
现在他的子民要替他承受这一切苦果
Whatever happens to his people is now on his head.
曾经我把他们视为我的同胞  若苏厄
Once I counted them as my people, Joshua.
我们的自由是有代价的
Our freedom comes at a price.
死亡天使
The angel of death
发现每户以色列人家都用鲜血做了标记
finds every Israelite house painted with blood,
逾越节(Passover)的来历
就放过了他们
and passes over.
为什么
Why?
为什么以色列奴隶还活着
Why should Israelite slaves have life,
而我儿子却死了
when my son is dead?
起来
Get up.
Get up!
滚
Go!
带着你们那卑鄙的天主  滚出我的国土
And leave my land, and take your wretched God with you!
东西都装好  准备走了
Load up, get ready.
快来  走吧
Come on, do it.
梅瑟
Moses!
我们要去完成亚巴郎与天主的圣约
We are going to fulfill Abraham's covenant with God.
去盟约之地繁衍生息
We're going to live in the promised land
拥有如繁星之多的后裔
with descendants as numerous as the stars.
我的孩子
My son.
奴隶怎可如此残忍
How could slaves do this?
我在此向你发誓
I vow to you, here and now,
我会把以色列人抓回来
that I will bring the Israelites back
让他们为你建造
and make them build you
世界上最宏伟的陵墓
the greatest tomb the world has ever seen.
用梅瑟的尸体
And Moses's body...
给陵墓奠基  给你陪葬
shall be buried in its foundations.
我还是不敢相信法郎就这么放了我们
I still can't believe Pharaoh just let us leave.
-他的确这样做了  -这是天主的旨意
- But he did. - It's what God demanded.
经过这么多事  只有疯子才会再次触怒天主
And only a madman would defy God again after what he's done.
红海
弟弟  接下来怎么办
Brother? What now?
弟弟
Brother?
天主会指引我们
God will provide a way.
梅瑟  为什么带我们来这
Moses. Why have you brought us here
是天主带我们来的
God brought us here.
那天主有没有说怎么过去
And what does God say about getting across?
埃及人  在山上
Egyptians, on the hill.
你的天主现在在哪啊  梅瑟
Where is your God now, Moses?
追到他们了  他们被困了
We have them! They're trapped!
格杀勿论
Die!
骑兵
Horses!
战车  他们追来了
Chariots! They're here!
埃及人追来了
The Egyptians.
蠢蛋  现在可如何是好
Fool! What do we do now?
是不是因为埃及没有我们的葬身之地
Or is it because there were no graves in Egypt
所以你带我们来这送死
that you brought us here to die?
看看你干的好事
Because that is what you've done!
他们来了  怎么办
They're coming! What do we do?
怎么办
Well?
梅瑟
Moses?
Moses!
主  我不相信
Lord, I cannot believe
这是你给我们安排的结局
this is the end you planned for us.
我们看着你给我们的敌人带去灾难
We have watched you bring terror on our enemies.
格杀勿论
Die!
将死亡隔绝于我们的门外
You kept death from our door.
-梅瑟  -梅瑟
- Moses! - Moses!
主啊
Lord!
天主与我们同在
God is with us!
跟我走
Follow me!
天主与我们同在
God is with us!
我们就从那直穿过去
We're going to go straight through there!
把大家集中到一起
Get your men together!
快点  快点
Hurry, hurry!
咱们得马上离开
We have to leave now!
快点燃火把
Light torches quickly!
快跑  快跑
Let's move! Let's move!
快跑  跑啊
Let's move! Move it!
-快走  -快点  快点
- Let's move! - Quickly! Hurry!
快跟上
Come on!
要有信德
Have faith!
快点
Come on!
别停下
Keep moving!
快
Hurry!
别怕
Don't be afraid!
要有信德
Have faith!
-快跑  -快跑  别停下来
- Come on! - Come on! Keep going!
等等
Wait!
给我追
After them!
进攻
Attack!
快
Now!
给我活捉梅瑟
Bring me Moses!
快跑 快跑
Run! Run!
跑啊
Run!
接着跑
Keep moving!
快点
Hurry!
我看到他们的火把了
I see their torches!
快跑  别停下
Come on! Keep moving!
他们追来了
They're coming.
快点
Hurry!
快跑
Run!
快啊
Hurry!
马上就要到了
We're almost there!
坚持住
Come on!
坚持住  老伙计
Come on, old man!
快点  快点
Hurry! Hurry!
我们到了
We're here!
他们还在追过来
They're still coming!
法郎  你不是天主
You are not a God, Pharaoh.
世上只有一位天主
There is only one God...
而他在这里
And he is here
与我们同在
with us.
不
No!
梅瑟
Moses.
自由了
Freedom!
我的同胞
My friends!
我的族人
My... People.
天主让我们摆脱了奴役
God has delivered us from slavery.
我们自由了
We are free.
你们已经历了漫长的跋涉
You have come a long way.
我知道
I know.
但我们的征途才刚刚开始
But our journey is just beginning.
我们必须信赖天主
We must trust in God.
必须跟随他所指引的道路
We must follow his path.
梅瑟领导以色列人来到了西乃山
Moses leads the Israelites to Mount Sinai,
在这里  天主在燃烧的荆棘中
where God first spoke to him
第一次与他对话
in the burning bush.
天主将刻在石头上的法典赐予了梅瑟
God gives laws to Moses, written in stone.
这就是《十诫》
The Ten Commandments.
若苏厄
Joshua.
天主
God has...
重申了他对亚巴郎许下的承诺
renewed the promise he made to Abraham.
我们有了助我们夺取盟约之地的新法律
We have new laws, preparing us for the promised land.
如果我们忠于天主  他一定会遵守诺言
If we are true to God, he will keep his promise.
亚巴郎的梦想
Abraham's dream.
我们的未来
Our future.
你是我们族人的未来  若苏厄
You are our people's future, Joshua.
你必须攻下那块本属于亚巴郎
You must take the land promised to Abraham
和他那多如繁星的子孙后代的
and all of his descendants,
盟约之地
as numerous as the stars.
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on the Bible
天主将我们从埃及解救出来
The Lord brought us out from Egypt.
他承诺会将这块土地赐予我们
He promised us this land.
很快
And soon...
它就会是我们的了
it will be ours!
我们必须攻下耶利哥
We must take Jericho.
找一条能让我进去的路
Just find me a way in.
若苏厄
Joshua!
他们知道天主与我们同在
The people melt in fear
都陷入恐慌  不战自溃
because they know he is with us.
天主确实与我们同在
God is with us!
上主为梅瑟将海水分开
The Lord parted the waters for Moses.
而为你  上主将岩石崩裂
For you he will split rock.
耶利哥是我们的
Jericho is ours!
只要我们遵从主
If we obey Lord,
一切
Anything...
皆有可能
is possible!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
天主会允你一个儿子
God will give you a son.
你的力量源自天主
Your strength comes from God.
三松  你背负着赶走培肋舍特人的使命
Samson, your duty is to drive the Philistines away.
您想让我怎么办
What would you have me do?
抛弃我爱的女人
Reject the woman I fell in love with
就因为她是培肋舍特人吗
just because she's a Philistine?
我们得给以色列人点颜色瞧瞧
We need to send these Israelites a message,
我们的女人不是他们可以染指的
They cannot take our women.
为吾妻
For my wife!
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
我叫德里拉
My name is Delilah.
你为何如此强壮
Why are you so strong?
天主与我同在  德里拉
God is with me, Delilah.
他赐我神力
He makes me strong.
倘若我剪了头发  天主会收回我的神力
If I cut my hair, my God will take away all my strength.
你做了什么
What have you done?
每个人都有自己的价码
Everyone has their price.
你的天主遗弃了你
Your God has deserted you
收回了你的神力
and taken your strength with him.
不  他要我彻底毁灭你们
No. He wants me to destroy you all!
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!